Chris Anderson: This is sucha strange thing.
Your software, Linux,is in millions of computers,
it probably powers much of the Internet.
And I think that there are, like,
a billion and a half activeAndroid devices out there.
Your software is in everysingle one of them.
It&amp;#39;s kind of amazing.
You must have some amazingsoftware headquarters driving all this.
That&amp;#39;s what I thought -- and I was shockedwhen I saw a picture of it.
I mean, this is --
this is the Linux world headquarters.
(Laughter)
(Applause)
Linus Torvalds: It reallydoesn&amp;#39;t look like much.
And I have to say,
the most interesting part in this picture,
that people mostly react to,
is the walking desk.
It is the most interestingpart in my office
and I&amp;#39;m not actually using it anymore.
And I think the two things are related.
The way I work is ...
I want to not have external stimulation.
You can kind of see,on the walls are this light green.
I&amp;#39;m told that at mental institutionsthey use that on the walls.
(Laughter)
It&amp;#39;s like a calming color,
it&amp;#39;s not somethingthat really stimulates you.
What you can&amp;#39;t see is the computer here,you only see the screen,
but the main thing I worryabout in my computer is --
it doesn&amp;#39;t have to be bigand powerful, although I like that --
it really has to be completely silent.
I know people who work for Google
and they have their ownsmall data center at home,
and I don&amp;#39;t do that.
My office is the mostboring office you&amp;#39;ll ever see.
And I sit there alone in the quiet.
If the cat comes up,
it sits in my lap.
And I want to hear the cat purring,
not the sound of the fans in the computer.
CA: So this is astonishing,
because working this way,
you&amp;#39;re able to run this vasttechnology empire --
it is an empire --
so that&amp;#39;s an amazing testamentto the power of open source.
Tell us how you gotto understand open source
and how it leadto the development of Linux.
LT: I mean, I still work alone.
Really -- I work alone in my house,
ofte in my bathrobe.
When a photographer shows up, I dress up,
so I have clothes on.
(Laughter)
And that&amp;#39;s how I&amp;#39;ve always worked.
I mean, this was how I started Linux, too.
I did not start Linuxas a collaborative project.
I started it as onein a series of many projects
I had done at the time for myself,
partly because I needed the end result,
but even more because I justenjoyed programming.
So it was about the end of the journey,
which, 25 years later,we still have not reached.
But it was really about the factthat I was looking for a project on my own
and there was no open source,really, on my radar at all.
And what happened is ...
the project grows and becomes somethingyou want to show off to people.
Really, this is more of a, &amp;quot;Wow,look at what I did!&amp;quot;
And trust me -- it was notthat great back then.
I made it publicly available,
and it wasn&amp;#39;t evenopen source at that point.
At that point it was source that was open,but there was no intention
behind using the kind of open-sourcemethodology that we think of today
to improve it.
It was more like,
&amp;quot;Look, I&amp;#39;ve been workingon this for half a year,
I&amp;#39;d love to have comments.&amp;quot;
At the University of Helsinki,
I had a friend who was oneof the open source --
it was called mainly&amp;quot;free software&amp;quot; back then --
and he actually introduced meto the notion that, hey,
you can use these open-sourcelicenses that had been around.
And I thought about it for a while.
I was actually worried about the wholecommercial interests coming in.
I mean, that&amp;#39;s one of the worriesI think most people who start out have,
is that they worry about somebodytaking advantage of their work, right?
And I decided, &amp;quot;What the hell?&amp;quot;
And --
CA: And then at some point,
someone contributedsome code that you thought,
&amp;quot;Wow, that really is interesting,I would not have thought of that.
This could actually improve this.&amp;quot;
LT: It didn&amp;#39;t even startby people contributing code,
it was more that peoplestarted contributing ideas.
And just the fact that somebody elsetakes a look at your project --
and I&amp;#39;m sure it&amp;#39;s trueof other things, too,
but it&amp;#39;s definitely true in code --
is that somebody elsetakes an interest in your code,
looks at it enough to actuallygive you feedback
and give you ideas.
That was a huge thing for me.
I was 21 at the time, so I was young,
but I had already programmedfor half my life, basically.
And every project before thathad been completely personal
and it was a revelation when peoplejust started commenting,
started giving feedback on your code.
And even before they startedgiving code back,
that was, I think, one of the bigmoments where I said,
&amp;quot;I love other people!&amp;quot;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong --
I&amp;#39;m actually not a people person.
(Laughter)
I don&amp;#39;t really love other people --
But I love computers,
I love interacting with otherpeople on email,
because it kind of gives you that buffer.
But I do love other people who commentand get involved in my project.
And it made it so much more.
CA: So was there a momentwhen you saw what was being built
and it suddenly started taking off,
and you thought, &amp;quot;Wait a sec,this actually could be something huge,
not just a personal projectthat I&amp;#39;m getting nice feedback on,
but a kind of explosive developmentin the whole technology world&amp;quot;?
LT: Not really.
I mean, the big point for me, really,was not when it was becoming huge,
it was when it was becoming little.
The big point for me was not being alone
and having 10, maybe 100people being involved --
that was a big point.
Then everything else was very gradual.
Going from 100 people to a million peopleis not a big deal -- to me.
Well, I mean, maybe it is if you&amp;#39;re --
(Laughter)
If you want to sell your resultthen it&amp;#39;s a huge deal --
don&amp;#39;t get me wrong.
But if you&amp;#39;re interested in the technology
and you&amp;#39;re interested in the project,
the big part was getting the community.
Then the community grew gradually.
And there&amp;#39;s actually nota single point where I went like,
&amp;quot;Wow, that just took off!&amp;quot; because it --
I mean -- it took a long time, relatively.
CA: So all the technologiststhat I talk to really credit you
with massively changing their work.
And it&amp;#39;s not just Linux,
it&amp;#39;s this thing called Git,
which is this management systemfor software development.
Tell us briefly about thatand your role in that.
LT: So one of the issues we had,
and this took a while to start to appear,
is when you ...
When you grow from having 10 peopleor 100 people working on a project
to having 10,000 people, which --
I mean, right now we&amp;#39;re in the situationwhere just on the kernel,
we have 1,000 people involvedin every single release
and that&amp;#39;s every two months,roughly two or three months.
Some of those people don&amp;#39;t do a lot.
There&amp;#39;s a lot of peoplewho make small, small changes.
But to maintain this,
the scale changes howyou have to maintain it.
And we went through a lot of pain.
And there are whole projectsthat do only source-code maintenance.
CVS is the one that used to bethe most commonly used,
and I hated CVS with a passionand refused to touch it
and tried something elsethat was radical and interesting
and everybody else hated.
CA: (Laughs)
LT: And we were in this bad spot,
where we had thousands of peoplewho wanted to participate,
but in many ways,I was the kind of break point,
where I could not scale to the point
where I could workwith thousands of people.
So Git is my second big project,
which was only created for meto maintain my first big project.
And this is literally how I work.
I don&amp;#39;t code for --
well, I do code for fun --
but I want to codefor something meaningful
so every single project I&amp;#39;ve ever donehas been something I needed
and --
CA: So really, both Linuxand Git kind of arose
almost as an unintended consequence
of your desire not to haveto work with too many people.
LT: Absolutely. Yes.
(Laughter)
CA: That&amp;#39;s amazing.LT: Yeah.
(Applause)
And yet, you&amp;#39;re the manwho&amp;#39;s transformed technology
not just once but twice,
and we have to tryand understand why it is.
You&amp;#39;ve given us some clues, but ...
Here&amp;#39;s a picture of you as a kid,with a Rubik&amp;#39;s Cube.
You mentioned that you&amp;#39;ve beenprogramming since you were like 10 or 11,
half your life.
Were you this sort of computergenius, you know, übernerd,
were you the star at schoolwho could do everything?
What were you like as a kid?
LT: Yeah, I think I wasthe prototypical nerd.
I mean, I was ...
I was not a people person back then.
That&amp;#39;s my younger brother.
I was clearly more interestedin the Rubik&amp;#39;s Cube
than my younger brother.
(Laughter)
My younger sister,who&amp;#39;s not in the picture,
when we had family meetings --
and it&amp;#39;s not a huge family, but I have,like, a couple of cousins --
she would prep me beforehand.
Like, before I steppedinto the room she would say,
&amp;quot;OK. That&amp;#39;s so-and-so ...&amp;quot;
Because I was not --
I was a geek.
I was into computers,
I was into math,
I was into physics.
I was good at that.
I don&amp;#39;t think I wasparticularly exceptional.
Apparently, my sister said
that my biggest exceptional qualitywas that I would not let go.
CA: OK, so let&amp;#39;s go there,because that&amp;#39;s interesting.
You would not let go.
So that&amp;#39;s not about beinga geek and being smart,
that&amp;#39;s about being ... stubborn?
LT: That&amp;#39;s about being stubborn.
That&amp;#39;s about, like,
just starting something
and not saying, &amp;quot;OK, I&amp;#39;m done,let&amp;#39;s do something else --
Look: shiny!&amp;quot;
And I notice that in manyother parts in my life, too.
I lived in Silicon Valley for seven years.
And I worked for the samecompany, in Silicon Valley,
for the whole time.
That is unheard of.
That&amp;#39;s not how Silicon Valley works.
The whole point of Silicon Valleyis that people jump between jobs
to kind of mix up the pot.
And that&amp;#39;s not the kind of person I am.
CA: But during the actualdevelopment of Linux itself,
that stubbornness sometimes broughtyou in conflict with other people.
Talk about that a bit.
Was that essential to sort of maintainthe quality of what was being built?
How would you describe what happened?
LT: I don&amp;#39;t know if it&amp;#39;s essential.
Going back to the &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m nota people person,&amp;quot; --
sometimes I&amp;#39;m also ...
shall we say,
&amp;quot;myopic&amp;quot; when it comesto other people&amp;#39;s feelings,
and that sometimes makes yousay things that hurt other people.
And I&amp;#39;m not proud of that.
(Applause)
But, at the same time, it&amp;#39;s --
I get people who tell methat I should be nice.
And then when I try to explain to themthat maybe you&amp;#39;re nice,
maybe you should be more aggressive,
they see that as me being not nice.
(Laughter)
What I&amp;#39;m trying to sayis we are different.
I&amp;#39;m not a people person;
it&amp;#39;s not somethingI&amp;#39;m particularly proud of,
but it&amp;#39;s part of me.
And one of the thingsI really like about open source
is it really allows differentpeople to work together.
We don&amp;#39;t have to like each other --
and sometimes we reallydon&amp;#39;t like each other.
Really -- I mean, there are very,very heated arguments.
But you can, actually,you can find things that --
you don&amp;#39;t even agree to disagree,
it&amp;#39;s just that you&amp;#39;re interestedin really different things.
And coming back to the pointwhere I said earlier
that I was afraid of commercial peopletaking advantage of your work,
it turned out, and veryquickly turned out,
that those commercial peoplewere lovely, lovely people.
And they did all the things that I was notat all interested in doing,
and they had completely different goals.
And they used open source in waysthat I just did not want to go.
But because it was opensource they could do it,
and it actually worksreally beautifully together.
And I actually thinkit works the same way.
You need to have the people-people,the communicators,
the warm and friendly people
who like --
(Laughter)
really want to hug youand get you into the community.
But that&amp;#39;s not everybody.
And that&amp;#39;s not me.
I care about the technology.
There are people who care about the UI.
I can&amp;#39;t do UI to save my life.
I mean, if I was stranded on an island
and the only way to get off that islandwas the make a pretty UI,
I&amp;#39;d die there.
(Laughter)
So there&amp;#39;s different kinds of people,
and I&amp;#39;m not making excuses,I&amp;#39;m trying to explain.
CA: Now, when we talked last week,
you talked about someother trait that you have,
which I found really interesting.
It&amp;#39;s this idea called taste.
And I&amp;#39;ve just got a couple of images here.
I think this is an example of notparticularly good taste in code,
and this one is better taste,
which one can immediately see.
What is the difference between these two?
LT: So this is --
How many people here actually have coded?
CA: Oh my goodness.
LT: So I guarantee you,
everybody who raised their hand,
they have done what&amp;#39;s calleda singly-linked list.
And it&amp;#39;s taught --
This, the first not verygood taste approach,
is basically how it&amp;#39;s taught to be donewhen you start out coding.
And you don&amp;#39;t have to understand the code.
The most interesting part to me
is the last if statement.
Because what happensin a singly-linked list --
this is trying to removean existing entry from a list --
and there&amp;#39;s a differencebetween if it&amp;#39;s the first entry
or whether it&amp;#39;s an entry in the middle.
Because if it&amp;#39;s the first entry,
you have to changethe pointer to the first entry.
If it&amp;#39;s in the middle,
you have to change the pointerof a previous entry.
So they&amp;#39;re two completely different cases.
CA: And that&amp;#39;s better.
LT: And this is better.
It does not have the if statement.
And it doesn&amp;#39;t really matter --
I don&amp;#39;t want you understandwhy it doesn&amp;#39;t have the if statement,
but I want you to understand
that sometimes you can seea problem in a different way
and rewrite it so thata special case goes away
and becomes the normal case.
And that&amp;#39;s good code.
But this is simple code.
This is CS 101.
This is not important --although, details are important.
To me, the sign of peopleI really want to work with
is that they have good taste,which is how ...
I sent you this stupid example
that is not relevantbecause it&amp;#39;s too small.
Good taste is much bigger than this.
Good taste is about reallyseeing the big patterns
and kind of instinctively knowingwhat&amp;#39;s the right way to do things.
CA: OK, so we&amp;#39;re puttingthe pieces together here now.
You have taste,
in a way that&amp;#39;s meaningfulto software people.
You&amp;#39;re --
(Laughter)
LT: I think it was meaningfulto some people here.
CA: You&amp;#39;re a very smart computer coder,
and you&amp;#39;re hellish stubborn.
But there must be something else.
I mean, you&amp;#39;ve changed the future.
You must have the abilityof these grand visions of the future.
You&amp;#39;re a visionary, right?
LT: I&amp;#39;ve actually felt slightlyuncomfortable at TED
for the last two days,
because there&amp;#39;s a lotof vision going on, right?
And I am not a visionary.
I do not have a five-year plan.
I&amp;#39;m an engineer.
And I think it&amp;#39;s really --
I mean -- I&amp;#39;m perfectlyhappy with all the people
who are walking aroundand just staring at the clouds
and looking at the starsand saying, &amp;quot;I want to go there.&amp;quot;
But I&amp;#39;m looking at the ground,
and I want to fix the potholethat&amp;#39;s right in front of me
before I fall in.
This is the kind of person I am.
(Cheers)
(Applause)
CA: So you spoke to me last weekabout these two guys.
Who are they and howdo you relate to them?
LT: Well, so this is kindof cliché in technology,
the whole Tesla versus Edison,
where Tesla is seen as the visionaryscientist and crazy idea man.
And people love Tesla.
I mean, there are people who nametheir companies after him.
(Laughter)
The other person there is Edison,
who is actually often vilifiedfor being kind of pedestrian
and is --
I mean, his most famous quote is,
&amp;quot;Genius is one percent inspirationand 99 percent perspiration.&amp;quot;
And I&amp;#39;m in the Edison camp,
even if people don&amp;#39;t always like him.
Because if you actually compare the two,
Tesla has kind of this mindgrab these days,
but who actually changed the world?
Edison may not have been a nice person,
he did a lot of things --
he was maybe not so intellectual,
not so visionary.
But I think I&amp;#39;m moreof an Edison than a Tesla.
CA: So our theme at TEDthis week is dreams --
big, bold, audacious dreams.
You&amp;#39;re really the antidote to that.
LT: I&amp;#39;m trying to dial it down a bit, yes.
CA: That&amp;#39;s good.
(Laughter)
We embrace you, we embrace you.
Companies like Google and manyothers have made, arguably,
like, billions of dollarsout of your software.
Does that piss you off?
LT: No.
No, it doesn&amp;#39;t piss me offfor several reasons.
And one of them is, I&amp;#39;m doing fine.
I&amp;#39;m really doing fine.
But the other reason is --
I mean, without doing the wholeopen source and really letting go thing,
Linux would never have been what it is.
And it&amp;#39;s brought experiencesI don&amp;#39;t really enjoy, public talking,
but at the same time,this is an experience.
Trust me.
So there&amp;#39;s a lot of things going onthat make me a very happy man
and thinking I did the right choices.
CA: Is the open source idea --
this is, I think we&amp;#39;ll end here --
is the open source ideafully realized now in the world,
or is there more that it could go,
are there more things that it could do?
LT: So, I&amp;#39;m of two minds there.
I think one reason open sourceworks so well in code
is that at the end of the day,
code tends to be somewhat black and white.
There&amp;#39;s often a fairly good way to decide,
this is done correctlyand this is not done well.
Code either works or it doesn&amp;#39;t,
which means that there&amp;#39;s lessroom for arguments.
And we have arguments despite this, right?
In many other areas --
I mean, people have talked aboutopen politics and things like that --
and it&amp;#39;s really hard sometimes to say
that, yes, you can apply the sameprinciples in some other areas
just because the black and whiteturns into not just gray,
but different colors.
So, obviously open source in scienceis making a comeback.
Science was there first.
But then science ended upbeing pretty closed,
with very expensive journalsand some of that going on.
And open source is makinga comeback in science,
with things like arXiv and open journals.
Wikipedia changed the world, too.
So there are other examples,
I&amp;#39;m sure there are more to come.
CA: But you&amp;#39;re not a visionary,
and so it&amp;#39;s not up to you to name them.
LT: No.
(Laughter)
It&amp;#39;s up to you guys to make them, right?
CA: Exactly.
Linus Torvalds,
thank you for Linux,thank you for the Internet,
thank you for all those Android phones.
Thank you for coming here to TEDand revealing so much of yourself.
LT: Thank you.
(Applause)